<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Patterns | प्रस्वेद: perspiration]]></title>
  <link href="http://prasveda.herokuapp.com/blog/categories/patterns/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://prasveda.herokuapp.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-05-26T14:19:49-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://prasveda.herokuapp.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Sage Vann]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[sagevann@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Observation 1: Patterns]]></title>
    <link href="http://prasveda.herokuapp.com/blog/2013/05/26/observation-1-patterns/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-26T12:25:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://prasveda.herokuapp.com/blog/2013/05/26/observation-1-patterns</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Sun, May 26 10:00am 90 min Fire + Water</h2>

<p>The room was warm, but not hot. I noticed that everyone seemed very focused, almost serious. <!-- more -->Having a chance to see how so many different bodies do this practice was good for me as it relates to my practice and to understanding how other people&rsquo;s bodies work into the poses. There were a lot of interesting &lsquo;trends&rsquo;, or similarities in many of the bodies. Here are some of the things I noticed.</p>

<ul>
<li>Many people, women in particular, actually push their chest&rsquo;s forward and almsost lean their upper body over their toes.</li>
<li>Twisting in the hips to compensate for a lack of thoracic flexibility is probably the most common &lsquo;cheat&rsquo;</li>
<li>Almost noone succeeds at having front thigh parallel in Trikonasana ( Bikram style ).</li>
<li>Tuladandasana seemed to be the pose that was troublesome for the most people. There were all sorts of adjustments by people that kept them out of the pose &lsquo;properly&rsquo;. I saw lots of chests up, hips rotated up, eyes at the mirror/eyes on fingers/eyes on floor. It was the posture with the least consistency amongst the group.</li>
<li>Floor bow also seemed to pose difficulties for many folks. I saw only a few practioners who got belly on the floor and lifted up from thighs.</li>
<li>Men sweat a lot more than women.</li>
<li>Ardha Shalabasana seems to be the most challenging floor pose. I saw few people with arms under body, and only one practictioner over 25-30degrees of leg lift.</li>
</ul>


<p>As I watched everyone else I noted a strong desire to video myself and see how I look. It doesn&rsquo;t come from an egoistic place so much as a curious place to see which of the patterns I noted that I also fall into. How many of the times that others cheated their hips forward to compensate for shoulders apply to me?</p>

<p>The other thing I noticed was that people give up at about 3 or 2 when you count down a posture. It&rsquo;s as if they&rsquo;ve given themselves permission to exit before 1 because the teacher is counting. It was a very intersting revelation.</p>

<p>Lastly, I found my urge to make adjustments nearly impossible to suppress. There were so many times I wanted to pop over and remind a practicioner of their hips, to tip a shoulder more up, to adjust toes, hands, or fingers on the floor. This experience definitely made me want to practice and teach more, and I can&rsquo;t wait to observe/assist again!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
