<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: pranayama, | प्रस्वेद: perspiration]]></title>
  <link href="http://prasveda.herokuapp.com/blog/categories/pranayama/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://prasveda.herokuapp.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-05-26T14:18:01-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://prasveda.herokuapp.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Sage Vann]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[sagevann@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pranayama Dialogue: Evolution]]></title>
    <link href="http://prasveda.herokuapp.com/blog/2013/05/26/pranayama-dialogue-evolution/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-26T13:35:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://prasveda.herokuapp.com/blog/2013/05/26/pranayama-dialogue-evolution</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It didn&rsquo;t take long before I realized that my dialogue was much too wordy. Also, it didn&rsquo;t carry much flow. I&rsquo;ve worked through and thought long and hard about how to tackle this section, and I came up with a three part strategy:</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>My Strategy</h3>

<ol>
<li>Write my prose first. This is V1 the wordy dialogue.</li>
<li>Create a &lsquo;tactic&rsquo; for how I&rsquo;ll divide up the breaths. Make a note card of this as a tool.</li>
<li>Read it and time it, note differences, reduce words to fit.</li>
<li>Polish and practice.</li>
</ol>


<p>So now I&rsquo;m on v2, I&rsquo;ve yet to get any feedback from the TTTeachers so I&rsquo;m excited to do that. If any of you have any feedback after reading it, would love to hear it.</p>

<p>-Sage</p>

<h2>Pranayama Deep Breathing</h2>

<blockquote><p><strong>Inhale</strong> in through the nose. Elbows out and up to frame the face.</p>

<p><strong>Exhale</strong>. Press the head back with the hands, bring elbows together to touch in front.</p></blockquote>

<!-- -->


<blockquote><p><strong>Inhale</strong>. Feel the breath in the back of the throat. It should sound like a wheeze or a snore. Loud enough for everyone to hear.</p>

<p><strong>Exhale</strong>. Wide open mouth, H.A. &lsquo;Haaaa&rsquo; sound. Like ocean waves in the distance ( or fogging a mirror )</p></blockquote>

<!-- -->


<blockquote><p><strong>Inhale</strong> 1 2 3 4 5 6</p>

<p><strong>Exhale</strong> 6 5 4 3 2 1</p></blockquote>

<!-- -->


<blockquote><p><strong>Inhale</strong> Take the full six counts to fill the lungs. If you get full before six, hold your breath, we&rsquo;ll catch up.</p>

<p><strong>Exhale</strong> Smoothly. Don&rsquo;t whoosh all your air out at the beginning. Even breathing all six.</p></blockquote>

<!-- -->


<blockquote><p><strong>Inhale</strong> Arms and head move in unison. Chin down, arms up, shoulders relaxed.</p>

<p><strong>Exhale</strong> As elbows come down, draw a semicirle in front of the body. Elbows stay up above shoulders.</p></blockquote>

<!-- -->


<blockquote><p><strong>Inhale</strong> 1 2 3 4 5 6</p>

<p><strong>Exhale</strong> 6 5 4 3 2 1</p></blockquote>

<!-- -->


<blockquote><p><strong>Inhale</strong> Keep your belly firm. Check your legs, pull up on anything that has relaxed.</p>

<p><strong>Exhale</strong> Keep heels pressed into floor. Lift up chest, push all the air out with the abs.</p></blockquote>

<!-- -->


<blockquote><p><strong>Inhale</strong> This deep breathing connects your body and mind, acclimates us, and warms the body for our practice.</p>

<p><strong>Exhale</strong> These long exhales balance the CO2 and oxygen in the body, allowing or muscles to keep working for us.</p></blockquote>

<!-- -->


<blockquote><p><strong>Inhale</strong> Last two, make these the fullest yet. Open the chest, breath in.</p>

<p><strong>Exhale</strong> See if you can press out all the air and feel your elbows squeeze at the very last moment.</p></blockquote>

<!-- -->


<blockquote><p><strong>Inhale</strong> Last breath 1 2 3 4 5 6</p>

<p><strong>Exhale</strong> 6 5 empty your lungs 3 2 sqeeze belly.</p></blockquote>

<!-- -->


<blockquote><p><strong>Relax</strong></p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
