<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: pranayama | प्रस्वेद: perspiration]]></title>
  <link href="http://prasveda.herokuapp.com/blog/categories/pranayama/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://prasveda.herokuapp.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-05-28T22:48:22-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://prasveda.herokuapp.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Sage Vann]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[sagevann@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pranayama Dialogue: Evolution]]></title>
    <link href="http://prasveda.herokuapp.com/blog/2013/05/26/pranayama-dialogue-evolution/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-26T13:35:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://prasveda.herokuapp.com/blog/2013/05/26/pranayama-dialogue-evolution</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It didn&rsquo;t take long before I realized that my dialogue was much too wordy. Also, it didn&rsquo;t carry much flow. I&rsquo;ve worked through and thought long and hard about how to tackle this section, and I came up with a three part strategy:</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>My Strategy</h3>

<ol>
<li>Write my prose first. This is V1 the wordy dialogue.</li>
<li>Create a &lsquo;tactic&rsquo; for how I&rsquo;ll divide up the breaths. Make a note card of this as a tool.</li>
<li>Read it and time it, note differences, reduce words to fit.</li>
<li>Polish and practice.</li>
</ol>


<p>So now I&rsquo;m on v2, I&rsquo;ve yet to get any feedback from the TTTeachers so I&rsquo;m excited to do that. If any of you have any feedback after reading it, would love to hear it.</p>

<p>-Sage</p>

<h2>Pranayama Deep Breathing</h2>

<blockquote><p><strong>Inhale</strong> in through the nose. Elbows out and up to frame the face.</p>

<p><strong>Exhale</strong>. Press the head back with the hands, bring elbows together to touch in front.</p></blockquote>

<!-- -->


<blockquote><p><strong>Inhale</strong>. Feel the breath in the back of the throat. It should sound like a wheeze or a snore. Loud enough for everyone to hear.</p>

<p><strong>Exhale</strong>. Wide open mouth, H.A. &lsquo;Haaaa&rsquo; sound. Like ocean waves in the distance ( or fogging a mirror )</p></blockquote>

<!-- -->


<blockquote><p><strong>Inhale</strong> 1 2 3 4 5 6</p>

<p><strong>Exhale</strong> 6 5 4 3 2 1</p></blockquote>

<!-- -->


<blockquote><p><strong>Inhale</strong> Take the full six counts to fill the lungs. If you get full before six, hold your breath, we&rsquo;ll catch up.</p>

<p><strong>Exhale</strong> Smoothly. Don&rsquo;t whoosh all your air out at the beginning. Even breathing all six.</p></blockquote>

<!-- -->


<blockquote><p><strong>Inhale</strong> Arms and head move in unison. Chin down, arms up, shoulders relaxed.</p>

<p><strong>Exhale</strong> As elbows come down, draw a semicirle in front of the body. Elbows stay up above shoulders.</p></blockquote>

<!-- -->


<blockquote><p><strong>Inhale</strong> 1 2 3 4 5 6</p>

<p><strong>Exhale</strong> 6 5 4 3 2 1</p></blockquote>

<!-- -->


<blockquote><p><strong>Inhale</strong> Keep your belly firm. Check your legs, pull up on anything that has relaxed.</p>

<p><strong>Exhale</strong> Keep heels pressed into floor. Lift up chest, push all the air out with the abs.</p></blockquote>

<!-- -->


<blockquote><p><strong>Inhale</strong> This deep breathing connects your body and mind, acclimates us, and warms the body for our practice.</p>

<p><strong>Exhale</strong> These long exhales balance the CO2 and oxygen in the body, allowing or muscles to keep working for us.</p></blockquote>

<!-- -->


<blockquote><p><strong>Inhale</strong> Last two, make these the fullest yet. Open the chest, breath in.</p>

<p><strong>Exhale</strong> See if you can press out all the air and feel your elbows squeeze at the very last moment.</p></blockquote>

<!-- -->


<blockquote><p><strong>Inhale</strong> Last breath 1 2 3 4 5 6</p>

<p><strong>Exhale</strong> 6 5 empty your lungs 3 2 sqeeze belly.</p></blockquote>

<!-- -->


<blockquote><p><strong>Relax</strong></p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pranayama Deep Breathing: Dialogue (v1)]]></title>
    <link href="http://prasveda.herokuapp.com/blog/2013/05/23/pranayama-deep-breathing/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-23T17:22:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://prasveda.herokuapp.com/blog/2013/05/23/pranayama-deep-breathing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is my first go at markdown, octopress, AND yoga teaching. A lot of firsts in this blog post.</p>

<!-- more -->


<blockquote><p>Bring your feet together, toes and heels touch. Firm your legs from your ankles to your hips. Firm your lower belly, pulling it up and in. Keep this sensation the same for the full breathing sequence.</p></blockquote>

<!-- -->


<blockquote><p>Good, now interlace your fingers of both hands, cross your thumbs. Place your knuckles below your chin, thumbs touch the throat. Maintain contact between fingers and chin for the full ten breaths. Let’s begin.</p></blockquote>

<!-- -->


<blockquote><p><strong>Inhale</strong> deeply through the nose. Lift the elbows out and and up to frame the face. Shoulders relaxed, belly firm and pull toward the spine.</p>

<p><strong>Exhale</strong>, open your mouth wide. Press the head back with the hands, elbows drawing an arc at shoulder height as you bring them to touch</p></blockquote>

<!-- -->


<blockquote><p><strong>Inhale.</strong> Head down as you bring your elbows out and up. Try to feel the breath at the back of your throat. This will help make the beautiful oceanic sound we&rsquo;re looking for.</p></blockquote>

<!-- -->


<blockquote><p><strong>Exhale</strong>. Stretch your mouth wide, throat constricted try to feel the heat of breath escaping your lungs. Like the fire from the belly of a dragon.</p></blockquote>

<!-- -->


<blockquote><p><strong>Inhale</strong>. 1 2 Firm legs, strong belly. 3, 4, Draw the chest taller, 6. Pause.</p>

<p><strong>Exhale</strong>, head back. 6 5 4 look back, chest high, 3 2 1.</p></blockquote>

<!-- -->


<blockquote><p><strong>Inhale</strong>, smooth and even. Do your best to inhale the full six counts with every breath. Expand your ribs, chest, and let the lungs stretch.</p>

<p><strong>Exhale</strong>, release the breath fully. Don&rsquo;t whoosh, make this exhale as even as your inhale, a full six seconds. Elbows touch just as you press out the last puffs of air.</p></blockquote>

<!-- -->


<blockquote><p><strong>Inhale</strong>, our goal is to drop our head down and move our elbows up at exactly the same time. Smooth, even over the full six counts.</p>

<p><strong>Exhale</strong>, as we press our hands firmly into our chin we work to bring the elbows forward to touch without dropping below the shoulders. Again, take the full six counts, lungs empty, bully squeezing, elbows touch.</p></blockquote>

<!-- -->


<blockquote><p><strong>Inhale</strong>, 1 2 3 legs firm, 4 5 shoulder&rsquo;s relaxed. 6</p>

<p><strong>Exhale</strong>, 6 stretch the mouth, 5 4 huge oceanic wave sound 3 2 elbows touch 1.</p></blockquote>

<!-- -->


<blockquote><p><strong>Inhale</strong>, keep the legs firm, weight in the heels. Solid. Belly firm and up, arms up shoulder&rsquo;s relaxed.</p>

<p><strong>Exhale</strong>, the only parts of our body that change are the arms, belly, and head. Legs remain firm, belly pulls up and in, arms squeeze.</p></blockquote>

<!-- -->


<blockquote><p><strong>Inhale</strong>, these deep full body breaths expand the lung tissue, connect our mind to our body, and assist to warm up and aclimate the body to the heat.</p>

<p><strong>Exhale</strong>, keeping the large muscles of our legs and belly held firm during the poses builds up carbon dioxide in our bodies. These extended exhales helps us to alleviate that excess CO2 so our muscles can continue to work.</p></blockquote>

<!-- -->


<blockquote><p>Last two breaths, <strong>Inhale</strong>. Let&rsquo;s make these the fullest breaths so far. Drive the weight back into the heels, pull up through every muscle in the legs, arms way up.</p>

<p><strong>Exhale</strong>, really stretch the mouth wide. Big oceanic exhale as we use the abdominal muscles pulling in and up to press out all our air. Elbows high, eyes back.</p></blockquote>

<!-- -->


<blockquote><p><strong>Inhale</strong>, full 5 counts, 1, belly in, 2, eyes focused, 3, get taller, 4, 5, 6.</p>

<p>Last Exhale, 6 press head back, 5, arms move smooth, 4, eyes back, 3, belly up and in, 2, 1. CLAP Change.</p></blockquote>

<!-- -->


<blockquote><p>Slowly bring your body back to neutral, weight firm over your heels, eyes on your own eyes in the mirror. Try to keep your breath cadence nice and even. Resist the urge to twitch, or fidget. Let the shoulders relax, heart slightly up, bum and tail pulling slightly down.</p>

<p>Let’s get ready for our second set. Hands interlaced, up to your chins. Here we go, let’s make this one even more beautiful.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
